Finding Aid for International Organization of Good Templars records, 1855-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
International Organization of Good Templars records 1855-1970
International Organization of Good Templars.
9 oversize volumes
25.5 linear feet
851519 Bd 2; BD Outsize
International fraternal temperance lodge. Records of the National Grand Lodge and local lodges in Illinois, New York and Washington (including numerous Scandinavian-American lodges) containing correspondence, minute books, financial ledgers, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, proceedings, and periodicals; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited with the library by the organization (donor no. 4977 ) in 1970. Periodic additions have been received.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Independent Order of Good Templars was founded in Utica, New York, in 1851, when it was first known as the Knights of Jerico. The secret order admitted women on a equal basis and focused exclusively on promoting the temperance movement. The organization next became known as the International Order of Good Templars as the movement spread to England and Scandinavia. Around 1969, the name of the organization was changed to the International Organization of Good Templars.
The organization flourished in the late nineteenth century with the immigration of Scandinavians to the mid-west. Because of language and cultural issues, the national organization of the IOGT permitted the Scandinavian Templars to form separate local lodges within each state's Grand Lodge.
Although the record group does include some correspondence, the bulk of the records consist of minute books and financial ledgers, mainly from the 1880s up to 1920. Many of these are for lodges in Illinois and Washington State. In addition, there are published materials, such as temperance books, pamphlets, and issues of periodicals. The proceedings of annual meetings are from many more states and provide detailed information on the national importance of the organization. The photographs are mainly of various group meetings.
Subjects:
United States--Emigration and immigration.; Illinois.; New York (State); Prohibition--United States.; Scandinavian Americans.; Temperance--United States.; Washington (State); Scandinavia--Emigration and immigration.; Immigrants--United States.; Immigrants--United States--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fraternal organizations.; International Organization of Good Templars.; Scandinavian Americans.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - 1886-1969, 12 folders (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous papers
  - Undated 1873-1970, 20 folders (Box 1)
- Bound minute books and financial ledgers
  - Lodges in Illinois
    - Jupiter Lodge 1884-1984, 26 volumes (Box 2-3)
      (returned to donor, November 2002)
    - Jupiter Lodge 1890-1895 (Box 2-3)
      (oversize volume, returned to donor, November 2002)
    - Framat Lodge 1908-1951, 7 volumes (Box 4)
    - Framat Lodge 1908-1951, 4 volumes (Box 5)
    - Swedish Home for Temperance 1892-1895 (Box 5)
    - Nordlyset Lodge 1914-1917 (Box 5)
    - Verdandi Lodge 1913-1918 (Box 5)
    - Facklan Lodge 1912-1919 (Volume 1)
    - Facklan Lodge 1912-1966, 12 volumes (Box 6)
    - True Unity Lodge 1938-1956 (Box 6)
    - Nornan Lodge 1913-1918 (Box 6)
    - Styrlanders Minne 1906-1915 (Box 7)
    - Scandia Lodge 1918-1946, 4 volumes (Box 7)
    - Ledsstjarnan Lodge 1921-1923, 2 volumes (Box 7)
    - Vega Lodge 1912-1934, 5 volumes (Box 8)
    - Lake View Kernel 1927-1962, 14 volumes (Box 8)
    - Solstralens Lodge 1913-1915 (Box 9)
    - Trofast Lodge 1903-1950 (Box 9)
    - Nordstjarnan Lodge 1929-1936 (Box 9)
    - Sangkaren Linnea 1916-1918 (Box 9)
    - Swedish Good Templars Mutual Aid Society 1899-1906 (Box 9)
    - Unity Co-op cafe 1931-1940, 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - Rockford Lodge No. 6 1910-1957, 11 volumes (Box 10)
    - Rockford Lodge No. 6 1910-1957, 3 volumes (Box 11)
    - Swedish Good Templar Building Association 1914-1943 (Box 11)
    - Camp Elwood 1928-1961 (Box 11)
    - Women's Chorus 1931-1945 (Box 11)
    - District Lodge No. 1 1907-1941, 3 volumes (Box 12)
    - District Lodge No. 2 1950-1963 (Box 12)
    - District Lodge No. 4 1908-1943, 2 volumes (Box 12)
    - District Lodge No. 5 1911-1919 (Volume 2)
    - District Lodge No. 5 1919-1928 (Box 12)
    - District Lodge No. 14 1903-1911 (Volume 3)
    - Unidentified Illinois Record Books, 2 volumes (Box 12)
    - Unidentified Illinois Record Books, 11 volumes (Box 13)
  - Lodges in Washington
    - Seattle Lodge No. 6 1866-1922, 7 volumes (Box 14)
    - Seattle Lodge No. 6 1866-1922, 10 volumes (Box 15)
    - Silver Star Lodge 1927-1930, 4 volumes (Box 15)
    - Arbetet Lodge 1916-1917 (Box 15)
    - Perseverance Lodge 1908-1911 (Box 15)
    - Norge Lodge 1905-1927, 19 volumes (Box 16)
    - Loyal Lodge 1904-1906 (Box 16)
    - Unidentified and miscellaneous Washington Record Books, 2 volumes (Box 16)
  - Lodges in other states
    - New York. Niagara District Lodge 1905-1910 (Box 17)
    - New Jersey. Pavonia Lodge 1870-1874 (Box 17)
    - Massachusetts. Quincy Lodge No. 5 1908-1945, 2 volumes (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous
  - Manuscript newspaper Lysglint 1913-1916, 2 volumes (Box 17)
  - Ritual books (Box 17)
  - Unidentified volumes (Volume 4)
- Published materials
  - Temperance books and pamphlets 1865-1963
    (in Swedish and Norwegian)
    - Temperance books and pamphlets 1865-1963 (Box 18)
    - Temperance books and pamphlets 1865-1963 (Box 19)
      (continued)
  - Newspaper clippings re International Supreme Lodge meeting 1895 (Box 20)
  - Various clippings 1896-1969, 5 folders (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, 1932-1934 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbooks, 1909-1921, 2 volumes (Volume 5)
  - Notebook re District Lodge No. 2 of the Central States Grand Lodge (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous temperance pamphlets (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous temperance pamphlets (Box 21)
  - Periodicals
    - Fyrtornet, 1903-1910 (Box 21)
    - Midsummer News, 1926-19-- (Box 21)
    - Dansk Good Templar, 1884-1887 (Box 21)
    - Scandinaviska Good Templaren, 1919-1935 (Box 22)
    - Bulletin of the Grand Lodge of Canada, 1965-1966 (Box 22)
    - Reformatorn, 1926-1964 (Box 22)
    - Vacation Breezes, 1954-1970 (Box 22)
    - Junior Temperance World, 1933-1949 (Box 22)
    - Temperance World, 1950-1960 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous temperance periodicals 1903-1969 (Box 22)
- Proceedings of Annual Meetings
  - R.W. Grand Lodge 1883 (Box 23)
  - Grand Lodge of Illinois 1855-1863, 1865-1869, 1877, 1888, 1892, 1904 (Box 23)
  - Scandinavian Grand Lodge of Illinois 1907-1939 (Box 23)
  - Central States Grand Lodge 1940-1969 (Box 23)
  - Northwest Grand Lodge 1948-1962 (Box 23)
  - International Supreme Lodge 1911-1966 (Box 24)
  - Good Templar Park Association 1925-1968 (Box 24)
  - Co-operative Temperance Cafe "Idrott" 1920-1930 (Box 24)
  - Western Scandinavian Grand Lodge 1912-1917 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of Washington 1909-1915 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of England (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of Scotland 1923-1926 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of New Jersey 1870 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of Wisconsin 1910-1911 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of Vermont 1900 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of Maryland, Virginia, and D.C. 1946-1947 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of Queensland (Australia) 1910 (Box 24)
  - Deutschen Guttemplerodens (Germany) 1926 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of Sweden 1918-1957 (Box 24)
  - Grand Lodge of the U.S. 1905-1966 (Box 25)
  - Grand Lodge of New York 1898-1970 (Box 25)
  - Grand Lodge of Denmark 1883-1893 (Box 25)
  - Tri-state Grand Lodge 1954-1962 (Box 26)
  - Connecticut Grand Lodge 1957-1962 (Box 26)
  - Grand Lodge of California 1962 (Box 26)
  - Grand Lodge of Finland 1955 (Box 26)
  - Eastern Grand Lodge 1927-1963 (Box 26)
  - Program books for various lodges (Box 26)
  - Yearbook 1978 (Box 26)
- Photographs
  - Group photographs, etc. (Box 27)
    (unprocessed)
  - Group photographs, etc. (Box 28)
Related Material
The Regional History Center of Northern Illinois University also has records of the International Organization of Good Templars.